The uniform code of military justice specifies
court martial for any officer who sends a
soldier into battle without a weapon.
There ought to be a similar protection
for students because students shouldn't go out
into life without an ability to communicate.
And that's because your success in life will
be determined largely by your ability to speak,
your ability to write, and the
quality of your ideas in that order.
I know that I can be successful
in this because the quality of communication.
Your speaking, your writing, is
largely determined by this formula.
It's a matter of how much knowledge you
have, how much you practice with that knowledge,
and your inherent talent.
And notice that the T is very small.
What really matters is what you know.
At this point that came to me suddenly a
few decades ago when I was skiing at Sun Valley.
I had heard that it was Celebrity Weekend.
And one of the celebrities...
Well, he was a famous comedian.
was Mary Lou Retton, famous Olympic gymnast,
perfect tens in the vault.
And I heard that she was a novice at skiing,
so when the opportune moment arrived,
I looked over on the novice slope
and saw this young woman who, when she became unbalanced,
went like that.
And I said, that's got to
be her, that must be the gymnast.
But then it occurred to me,
I'm a much better skier than she is,
and she's an Olympic athlete,
not only an ordinary Olympic athlete, an outstanding one.
And I was a better
skier because I had the K,
and I had the P, and
all she had was the T.
So you can get a lot better than people
who may have inherent talents
if you have the right amount of knowledge.
So that's what my objective is today,
and here's my promise.
Today you will see some examples
of what you can put in your armamentarium
of speaking techniques.
And it will be the case
that some one of those examples,
some heuristic, some technique, maybe only one,
will be the one that gets you the job.
And so this is a very nonlinear process.
You never know when it's gonna happen.
But that is my promise.
By the end of the next 60 minutes,
you'll have been exposed to a lot of ideas,
some of which you'll incorporate into your own repertoire,
and they will ensure that you get the maximum opportunity
to have your ideas valued and accepted
by the people you speak with.
Now, in order to do that,
we have to have a rule of engagement.
And that is no laptops, no cellphones.
So if you could close those, I'll start.
I'll start up as soon as you're done.
Some people ask why that is a rule of engagement.
And the answer is, we humans only have
one language processor.
And if your language processor is engaged,
could you shut the laptop please?
If your language processor is engaged,
browsing the web or reading your email,
you're distracted.
And worse yet, you distract all the people around you.
Studies have shown that.
And worse yet, if I see an open laptop,
somewhere back there or up here,
it drives me nuts.
And I do a worse job.
And so that ensures that all of your friends
who are paying attention don't get the performance
that they came to have.
So that's it for preamble.
Let's get started.
First thing to talk about,
of course, is how to start.
Some people think the right thing to do
is to start a talk with a joke.
I don't recommend it.
And the reason is that
in the beginning of a talk,
people are still putting their laptops away.
They're becoming adjusted to your speaking parameters,
to your vocal parameters.
And they're not ready for a joke.
So it doesn't work very well.
They usually fall flat.
What you want to do instead
is start with an empowerment promise.
You want to tell people what they're going to know
at the end of the hour that they didn't know
at the beginning of the hour.
It's an empowerment promise.
It's the reason for being here.
What would be an example?
Oh, I see.
At the end of this 60 minutes,
you will know things about speaking you don't know now.
And something among those things you know
will make a difference in your life.
Yeah, that's an empowerment promise.
So that's the best way to start.
So now that I've talked a
little bit about how to start,
what I want to do is
give you some samples of heuristics
that are always on my
mind when I give a talk.
And the first of these heuristics
is that it's a good idea
to cycle on the subject.
Go around it.
Go around it again.
Some people say, tell them
what you want to tell them.
Tell them again.
And then tell them a third time,
as if people weren't intelligent.
But the point is, the reason
is, well, there are many reasons,
one of which is at any given moment,
about 20% of you will be fogged
out no matter what the lecture is.
So if you want to ensure that the probability
that everybody gets it is high,
you need to say it three times.
So cycling is one of the
things that I always think about
when I give a talk.
Another thing I think about is in explaining my idea,
I want to build a fence around it
so that it's not confused with somebody else's idea.
So if you were from
Mars and I was teaching you
about what an arch is, I might
say to you, well, that's an arch.
And that's not to be confused with some other things
that other people might think is an arch.
This is not an arch.
That's not an arch.
I'm building a fence around my idea
so that it can be distinguished from somebody else's idea.
So in a more technical sense, I might say,
well, my algorithm might seem similar to Jones's algorithm,
except his is exponential and mine's linear.
That's putting a fence around your idea
so that people can not be confused
about how it might relate to something else.
The third thing on this list of samples
is the idea of verbal punctuation.
And the idea here is that because people will occasionally
fog out and need to get back on the bus,
you need to provide some landmark places
where you're announcing that it's a
good time to get back on.
So I might, in this talk,
say something about this being my outline.
The first thing we're going to
do is talk about how to start.
Then we're going to deal with these four samples.
And among these four samples,
I've talked about the first idea, that's cycling,
the second idea, building a fence.
And now the third idea is verbal punctuation.
So I'm enumerating, I'm providing numbers,
I'm giving you a sense that
there's a seam in the talk
and you can get back on.
Okay?
So now we're on a roll.
And since we're on a roll,
can you guess what fourth idea might be here?
An idea that helps people get back on the bus?
Ask a question.
Yes.
Ask a question, yes.
Thank you.
So ask a question.
And so I will ask a question.
How much dead air can there be?
How long can I pause?
I counted seven seconds.
It seems like an eternity to me
to wait and not say anything for seven seconds.
But that's the standard amount of time
you can wait for an answer.
And of course the question has to be carefully chosen.
It can't be too obvious
because then people will be embarrassed
to say what the answer is.
It can't be too hard
because then nobody will have anything to say.
So here are some sample heuristics
you can put in your armamentorium
and build up your repertoire of ideas about presentation.
And now if this persuades you
that there is something to know,
that there is knowledge,
then I've already succeeded.
Because what I want to convince you of
is that if you watch the speakers you admire
and feel are effective
and ask yourselves why they're successful,
then you can build up your own personal repertoire
and develop your own personal style.
And that's my fundamental objective.
And the rest of this talk
is about some of the
things that are in my armamentorium
that I think are effective.
So next thing on our agenda
as we start to discuss these other things
is a discussion of time and place.
So what do you think is
a good time to have a lecture?
11 a.m.
Yeah.
And the reason is
most people at MIT are awake by then
and hardly anyone is coming.
So they're just going back to sleep.
It's not right after a meal.
People aren't fatigued from this or that.
It's a great time to have a lecture.
So that brings me next to the question of
what about the place?
And the most important thing about the place
is that it be well lit.
This room is well lit.
The problem with other kinds of rooms
is that we humans,
whenever the lights go down,
whenever the room is dimly lighted,
it signals that we should go to sleep.
So whenever I go somewhere to give a talk,
even today,
the first thing I do
when I speak to the audiovisual people is say,
keep the lights full up.
Oh, they might reply,
people will see the slides better
if we turn the lights off.
And then I reply,
it's extremely hard to see slides through closed eyelids.
So I'm not sure if that's
the right way to do it.
But I think it's a good idea.
What else can you say about the place?
Well, the place should be cased.
And I mean that in a colloquial sense of,
like if you're robbing a bank,
you would go to the bank,
you know, some occasions before
to see what it's like,
so there are no surprises
when you do your robbery.
So whenever I go somewhere to say,
whenever I go somewhere to speak,
the first thing I ask my host to do
is to take me to
the place where I'll be speaking
so that if there are any weirdnesses,
I'll be able to deal with it.
Sometimes it might require some intervention.
Sometimes it just might require me to
understand what the challenges are.
So when I came here this morning,
I did what I typically do.
I imagined that all the seats were filled
with disinterested farm animals.
And I just went away.
I knew that no matter how bad it was,
it wouldn't be as bad as that.
So finally, it should be reasonably populated.
It should be the case that,
you know, if there were ten people in this hall,
everyone would be wondering what's going on
that's so much more interesting
than just a few people sitting in one place.
So you want to get a right-sized place
that doesn't have to be packed,
but it has to be more than half full.
So those are some thoughts about time and place.
The next thing I want to talk about
is the subject of boards and props and slides.
Well, these are the tools of the trade.
I believe that this is the right tool
for speaking when your purpose is informing.
The slides are good when your purpose is exposing.
But this is what I use when I'm informing,
teaching, lecturing.
And there are several reasons why I use it.
For one thing, when you use the board,
you have a graphic quality.
It's the case that when you have,
you know, a board,
then you can easily exploit the fact
that you can use graphics in your presentation.
So that's the graphic quality that I like.
And the next thing I like
is the like a speed property.
The speed with which you write on the blackboard
is approximately the speed
at which people can absorb ideas.
If you go flipping through a bunch of slides,
nobody can go that fast.
So, I'm going to show you
a little bit of a slide.
Finally, one great property of a board
is that it can be a target.
Many people who are novices at speaking
find themselves suddenly aware of their hands.
It's as if their hands were private parts
that shouldn't be exposed in public.
So right away they go into the pockets.
And this is considered insulting
in some parts of the world.
Or alternatively, maybe the hands will go
in back like this.
I was once in a convent in Serbia
and my host, well, we were,
as soon as we entered,
a nun came up to us
and offered us a refreshment.
And I was about to say, no, thank you,
when he said, eat that stuff or die.
It's a question of local custom and politeness.
But then, before anything happened there,
the nun pulled my hands off like this
because it was extraordinarily insulting
in that culture to have your hands behind your back.
So why is that?
Well, it's usually supposed that it has to do
with whether you're concealing a weapon.
So if your hands are in your pockets
or behind your back, then it looks like you
have a weapon.
And that's what I mean by the virtue,
one of these virtues of the board.
Now you have something to do with your hands.
You can point out the stuff.
I was once watching Seymour Papert give a lecture.
I thought it was terrific.
So I went a second time.
First time to absorb the content,
second time to note the style.
And what I discovered is that Papert was constantly
pointing at the board.
And then I thought about it a little while
and I noted that none of
the stuff he was pointing to
had anything to do with what he was saying.
Nevertheless, it was an effective technique.
So that's just a little
bit about the virtue of blackboards.
Now I want to talk about props.
You know, the custodians of knowledge about props
are the playwrights.
Many decades ago, I saw a play by Heinrich Ibsen.
It was Hedda Gabler.
I remember vaguely that it was about a woman
in an unhappy marriage.
And her husband was in competition for an academic job
with somebody else.
And he was going to lose,
partly because he was boring
and partly because the competitor had just written
a magnificent book.
By the way, this was back
in the days before there were
copying machines and computers.
Anyhow, as the play opens,
there's a pot-bellied stove.
And I'm going to show you
a little bit of the story
of the pot-bellied stove.
ご視聴ありがとうございました
And in the beginning of the play, the potbellied stove,
with its open door, just has some slightly glowing embers.
But the potbellied stove is always there,
and its tension mounts in the play.
And you see this manuscript, this prop,
that Ibsen so artfully used, you just know
that something's going to happen,
because as the play goes on,
the fire gets bigger and hotter,
and finally, all-consuming, you just know
that that manuscript is going to go into that fire.
It's a memorable thing, it's
what I remember about the play.
So the playwrights have got this all figured out,
but on the other hand, they're not the only people
who can use props.
Here's an example of the use of a prop,
also due to Seymour Papert, he was talking about
how it's important to look at
the problem in the right way.
And here's an example that not only teaches that,
but makes it possible for you to embarrass your friends
in mechanical engineering.
So here's what you do.
Take this bicycle wheel, and you start it spinning,
and then you put some torque on the axle.
Or, equivalently, you blow on the edge,
and the issue is, does it go that way,
or, does it go that way?
Now the mechanical engineers will immediately say,
oh yes, I see, right-hand screw wheel,
and they'll put their fingers in this position,
but forget exactly how to align their fingers
with various aspects of the problem.
And so it's usually the
case that they get it right
with about a 50% probability.
So their very fancy education
gets them up to the point
where they're equivalent.
And they're not.
They're just flipping a coin.
But it doesn't have to be that way,
because you can think about
the problem a little differently.
So here's what you do.
You take some duct tape,
and you put it around the
part of the wheel like that.
And now you start to
think about not the whole wheel,
but just the little piece that's underneath the duct tape.
So here that piece comes rolling over the top,
and at this point you blow
on it with a puff of air,
forgetting about the rest of the wheel, and you're done.
And the wheel, what happens to that little piece
that's under the duct tape?
It must want to go that way,
because you banged on it like that.
It's already going down like that.
And what about the next piece?
Same thing.
Next piece, same thing.
So the only thing that can happen
is that the wheel goes over like that.
And so now you'll never wonder again,
because you're thinking about the problem in the right way,
and it's demonstrated by the use of a prop.
You can try this after we're done.
Another example I like to remember
is one from when I was taking 801.
Alan Lazarus was the instructor at the time,
and he was talking about the conservation of energy,
kinetic and potential.
And there was a long
wire in the ceiling in 26100
attached to a much bigger steel ball,
but one not unlike this.
And Lazarus said,
I took the ball up against the wall like this.
He put his head flat
against the wall to steady himself,
and then he let go.
And the pendulum takes many
seconds to go over and back,
and then gently kisses Lazarus's nose.
And so you have many seconds to think,
this guy really believes in the conservation of energy.
Do not try this at home.
The problem is that the first time you do this,
you may not just let go.
There's a natural human tendency to push.
So that's a little bit on the subject of props.
You know, it's interesting.
Whenever surveys are taken,
students always say more chalk, less PowerPoint.
And why would that be?
Props are always also very effective.
Why would that be?
I'll give you my lunatic theory.
I'll give you my lunatic fringe view on this.
It has to do with what I would call
empathetic mirroring.
When you're sitting up there
watching me right on the board,
all those little mirror neurons in your head,
I believe, become actuated,
and you can feel yourself writing on the blackboard.
And even more so,
when I talk about this steel
ball going that way and this way,
you can feel the ball as if you were me.
And you can't do that with a slide.
You can't do it with a picture.
You need to see it in a physical world.
That's why I think that...
Oh, yes, of course, there are speed questions involved, too,
that have to be separated out.
But I think that empathetic mirroring is why props
and the use of a blackboard are so effective.
Well, let's see.
Oh, yes, there is one more
thing by way of the tools,
and that has to do with the use of slides.
I repeat, I think they're for exposing ideas,
not for teaching ideas,
but that's what we do in a job talk
or a conference talk.
We expose ideas.
We don't teach them.
So let me tell you a
little bit about my views on that.
I remember once I was
in Terminal A at Logan Airport.
I'd just come back from a really miserable conference,
and the flight was really horrible.
It was one of those that
feels like an unbalanced washing machine.
And for the only time in my life,
I decided to stop on my way to my car
and have a cup of
coffee and relax a little bit.
And as I was there for a few minutes,
someone came up to me and said,
are you Professor Winston?
I think so, I said.
I don't know.
I guess I was trying to be funny.
In any event, he said, I'm on my
way to Europe to give a job talk.
Would you mind critiquing my slides?
Not at all, I said.
You have too many, and they have too many words.
How did you know, he said,
thinking perhaps I'd seen a talk of his before.
I hadn't.
My reply was, because it's always true.
There are always too many slides, always too many words.
So let me show you some extreme
examples of how not to use slides.
Well, for this demonstration,
I need to be way over here.
And when I get over here, then
I can start to say things like,
one of the things you
shouldn't do is read your transparencies.
People in your audience know how to read,
and reading will just annoy them.
Also, you should be sure that you
have only a few words on each transparency
and that the words are easy to read.
And I hope they're driving you crazy.
Because I'm committing, you know,
committing all kinds of crimes.
The first of which is that there
are too many words on the slide.
Second of which is I'm way over there,
and the slide's way over there.
So you get into this tennis match feeling
of shifting back and forth
between the slide and the speaker.
You want the slides to
be condiments to what you're saying,
not the main event or the opposite way around.
So how can we fix this?
Step number one,
is to get rid of the background junk.
That's always distraction.
Step number two is to get rid of the words.
When I reduce the words to these,
then everything I read a previous time,
I'm not licensed to say
because it's not on the slide.
I'm not reading my slides anymore,
but I'm saying what was written
on the slides in a previous example.
So what else can we do to simplify this?
Well, we can get rid of the logos.
We don't need them.
Simplification.
What else can we do?
Get rid of the title.
Now I want to talk to
you about some rules for slide preparation.
I'm telling you the title.
It doesn't have to be up there.
By reducing the number of words on the slide,
I'm allowing you to pay more attention to me
and less to what's written on the slide.
I mentioned it before.
We have only one language process.
And we can either use it to read stuff
or to listen to the speaker.
And so if we have
too many words on the slide,
it forces people in the audience
to read this stuff and not listen.
A student of mine did
an experiment a few years ago.
He taught some students some web-based programming ideas.
Half the information was on slides.
He said the other half.
And then for a control group, he reversed it.
And the question was, what did the subjects,
that is, a freshman in his fraternity,
what did the subjects remember best?
What he said or what they read on the slide?
And the answer is what they read on the slide.
When the slides have a lot of material on it,
they don't pay attention to the speaker.
In fact, in the after-action report,
one of the subjects said,
I wish you hadn't talked so much.
It was distracting.
Well, the last item is eliminate clutter.
Now, here's some clutter.
No reason even for those bullets.
So the too-many-words problem is a consequence
of a crime Microsoft has committed
by allowing you to use fonts that are too small.
So you should all have a sample slide like this
that you can use to determine
what the minimum font size is
that's easily legible.
Shibu, what do you think of those?
What's that?
Yeah.
Minimum, maybe.
Yeah, he says 40 or 50.
I think that's about right.
35 is if you can get too small.
Not necessarily because you can't read it,
but because you're probably using it
to get too many words on the slide.
What other crimes do we have?
Well, we have the laser pointer crime.
And for that, I brought a lot.
You know, in the old days,
when we didn't have laser pointers,
we used wooden ones,
and people would go waving these things around,
and pretty soon it became almost like
a baton swirling contest.
So here's what we're doing.
Here's what I recommended in the old days
for dealing with this kind of pointer.
This is an example of the use of a prop.
Jim Glass up there saw
this talk about 20 years ago
and said, oh, yeah, I remember that talk.
That's the one where you broke the pointer.
It's amazing how props tend to be
the things that are remembered.
Well, now we don't have,
we don't have,
we don't have physical pointers anymore.
We've got laser pointers.
It's a wonder more people aren't driven
into epileptic fits over this sort of stuff.
But here's what tends to happen.
Look at that.
It's a lovely recursive picture,
and I can become part of it
by putting that laser beam
right on the back of my head up there.
And what do you see?
You see the back of my head.
I have no eye contact, no engagement, nothing.
I was sitting with a
student watching a talk one day,
and she said, you know what?
We could all leave, and he wouldn't know.
So what happens when you use a laser pointer?
You can't use a laser pointer without
turning your head and pointing it at something.
And when you do that,
you lose contact with the audience.
You don't want to do it.
So what do you do if you,
you need to identify something in your image,
and you don't want to
point at it with a laser?
This is what you do.
Put a little arrow on there and say,
now look at that guy number one,
at the end of arrow number one.
You don't need to have
a laser pointer to do that.
The too heavy crime.
When people ask me to review a presentation,
I ask them to print it out
and lay it out on a table.
When they do that,
it's easy to see whether the talk is too heavy,
too much text,
not enough air,
not enough white space,
not enough imagery.
This is a good example of such a talk.
Way too heavy.
The presenter has taken advantage of
small font sizes to get as
much on the slide as he wanted.
Lots of other crimes here,
but the fact that it's too heavy
is what I wanted to illustrate.
So here, by contrast,
another talk,
one I gave a few years ago.
It wasn't a deeply technical talk,
but I show it to you because
there's air in it.
It's mostly pictures of things.
There are three or four
slides that have text on them,
but when I come to those,
I give the audience time to read them.
And they're there because they might have
some historical significance.
The first slide with a lot of text on it
is an extraction from the 1957,
from the proposal for the 1957
AI conference at Dartmouth.
Extraordinarily interesting event,
and that historical
extraction from the proposal
helps drive that point home.
What else have we got here?
Oh yeah, your vocabulary word for the day.
This is an Apax Legomenon.
What that means is,
this is the kind of
slide you can get away with
exactly once in your presentation.
This is a slide that
got some currency some years ago
because it shows the complexity
of governing in Afghanistan
by showing how impossibly complex it is.
It's something you in the audience can't understand,
and that's the point.
But you can't have many of these.
You can have one per work,
one per presentation,
one per paper,
one per book.
That's what Apax Legomenon is,
and this is an example of it.
Well, I'll show you some crimes,
and so you might be asking,
do these crimes actually occur?
So, they do.
There's the hands in the pockets crime.
There's a crime and time and place selection here.
This is how you get to the Bartos Theater.
First thing you do is you get on these steps
over at the Media Lab.
Then you cross this large open space.
Then you turn right down this corridor.
At this point, whenever I go in there,
I wonder if there are torture implements around the corner.
And then when you get in there,
you get into this dark, gloomy place.
So it's well-named when they call it the Bartos Theater
because it's a place where you can watch a movie,
but it's not a place
where you can give a talk.
Now, on a subject that doesn't happen,
here's a talk I attended a while back in Stata.
Notice that the speaker is far away from the slides.
The speaker's using a laser pointer.
It's a little bit more of a straight line.
He's using a laser pointer.
And you say to me, well, what's happening here?
It's, by the way, the 80th slide in the presentation.
Notice that it's dense with words.
This is the first of 10 conclusion slides.
So what's the audience reaction?
That's the sponsor of the meeting.
He's reading his email.
This is the co-sponsor of the meeting.
He's examining the lunch menu.
What about this person?
This person looks like he's paying attention,
but just because it's a still picture.
If you were to see a video,
what you would see is something like this.
So, yeah, it does happen.
Well, now, that's a little bit more of a story.
I think we've done a quick review of tools.
Now I want to talk about some special cases.
We could talk a little bit about informing,
or to say it another
way, doing what I'm doing now.
But I'll just say a few words about that.
In that kind of presentation, you
want to start with a promise,
like I did for this
hour that we're going through now.
But then it comes to the question of,
how do you inspire people?
I've given this talk for a long time,
and a few years ago our department chairman said,
would you please give this talk to a new faculty
and be sure to emphasize
what it takes to inspire students?
And strangely, I hadn't thought about that question before,
so I started a survey.
I talked to some of my incoming freshman advisees,
and I talked to senior faculty and everything in between
about how they've been inspired by this.
And what I found from the incoming freshman
is that they were inspired by some high school teacher
who told them they could do it.
What I found in the senior faculty,
they were inspired by someone who helped them
to see a problem in a new way.
And what I saw from
everyone is that they were inspired
when someone exhibited passion about what they were doing.
I used that.
Exhibit passion about what they were doing.
Yeah, so that's one way to be inspiring.
It's easy for me because, you know,
I do artificial intelligence.
And how can you not be interested
in artificial intelligence, right?
I mean, if you're not interested in artificial intelligence,
you're probably not interested in interesting things.
So when I'm lecturing in my,
in my AI class,
it's natural for me to talk
about what I think is cool
and how exciting some new idea is.
So that's the kind of,
that's the kind of expression of passion
that makes a difference while informing
with respect to this question of inspiring.
Oh, yeah, and of course, during this promise phase,
you can also express how cool stuff is.
Let me give you an example of a lecture
that starts this way.
I'm talking about resource allocation.
It's the same sort of stuff
you would think of when you're,
it's the same sort of ideas you would need
if you're allocating aircraft to a flight schedule
or trying to schedule a factory or something like that.
But the example is putting colors on the states
in the United States without any bordering states
having the same color.
So here goes.
This is what I show in my,
in the beginning of the class.
This is a way of doing that coloring.
And you might say,
well, why don't we wait till it finishes?
Would you like to do that?
No?
Well, we're not gonna wait till it finishes
because the sun will have exploded
and consumed the earth before this program finishes.
But with a slight adjustment to how the program works,
which I tell my students,
you will understand in the next 50 minutes,
this is what you get.
Isn't that cool?
You know, you gotta be amazed by stuff
that takes a computation from longer than the lifetime
of the solar system into a few seconds.
So that's what I mean
by providing a promise up front
and expressing some passion about what you're talking about.
Well, the last item in this little block here
has to do with what people
think that they do at MIT.
You ask faculty what the most important purpose is,
and they'll say, well,
the most important thing I do
is teach people how to think.
And then you say, oh, that's great.
How do you teach people how to think?
Blank stare.
No one can quite respond to that part,
that natural next question.
So how do you teach people how to think?
Well, I believe that we all have a purpose.
I believe that we are storytelling animals
and that we start developing our story,
understanding and manipulating skills
with fairy tales in childhood
and continue on through professional schools
like law, business, medicine, engineering, everything.
And we continue doing that throughout life.
So if that is what thinking is all about,
then when you want to teach people how to think,
you provide them with the stories they need to know,
the questions they need to ask about those stories,
mechanisms for analyzing those stories,
ways of putting stories together,
ways of evaluating how reliable a story is,
and that's what I think you need to do
when you teach people how to think.
But that's all about education,
and many of you here,
not necessarily for that,
but rather for this part,
for persuading,
which breaks down into several categories,
oral exams not shown,
job talks getting famous.
I won't say much about oral exams
other than the fact that they used to be
a lot scarier than they are today.
In the old days,
reading the literature in a foreign language
was part of that,
and there was a high failure rate.
And when you look back on those failures,
the most usual reason for people failing an oral exam
is failure to situate and failure to practice.
By situate, I mean it's important to talk about
your research in context.
This is a problem that's
being pursued all over the world.
There hasn't been any progress before me
in the past 30 years.
Everyone is looking for a solution
because it will have impact on so many other things.
So that's situating in time and place and feel.
And then as far as practice is concerned,
yes, practice is important,
but that doesn't mean showing your slides
to the people you share an office with.
The problem with that is that
if people know what you're doing,
they will hallucinate that there's material
in your presentation that isn't there.
A variation on this thing, by the way,
is your faculty supervisor
is not a very good person
to help you debug a talk
because they, in fact, know what you're doing,
and they will, in fact, hallucinate
there's material in your presentation that isn't there.
So you need to get together some friends
who don't know what you're doing and have them...
Well, you start the practice session by saying,
if you can't make me cry,
I won't value you as a friend anymore.
And then when you get to the faculty
on an oral exam, it will be easy.
You see, difficulty...
The amount of flak you'll get from somebody
is proportional to age.
The older somebody is,
the more they understand where they are in the world.
But the young people are
trying to show the old people
how smart they are, so they'll be vicious.
So whenever you have an opportunity
to have an examining committee
that's full of people with gray hair,
that's what you want.
Well, that's just a word or two
about something I haven't listed here.
Let's get into the subject of job talks.
So I was sitting in a bar
many years ago in San Diego.
I was a member of the Navy Science Board,
and I was sitting with a
couple of my colleagues on the board.
Dolores Eder from the University of Colorado.
She made me so jealous I could spit
because she'd written 21 books
and I'd only written 17.
And then the other one was
Bill Weldon from the University of Texas.
He was an electromagnet.
He was a magnetism guy,
and he knew how to use rail guns
to drive steel rods through tank armor.
These were interesting people.
So I said, what do you look for
in a faculty candidate?
And within one microsecond,
Dolores said,
they have to show us
they've got some kind of vision.
Quickly followed by Bill,
who said, they have to show us
that they've done something.
Oh, that sounds good, I said.
And then I said to them,
how long does a candidate have
to establish these two things?
What do you think?
Well, compare your answer to theirs.
Five minutes.
So if you haven't expressed your vision,
if you haven't told people
that you've done something,
in five minutes you've already lost.
So you have to be able to do that.
And let me just mention a couple of things
in that connection.
Here, which is, you know, the vision
is in part a problem that somebody cares about
and something new in your approach.
So the problem is understanding
the nature of human intelligence.
And the approach is asking questions
about what makes us different
from chimpanzees and Neanderthals.
Is it merely a matter of quantity
or are we just a little bit smarter
in some continuous way?
Or do we have something that's fundamentally different
that chimpanzees don't have
and Neanderthals either?
And the answer is yes.
We do have something different.
We are symbolic creatures.
And because we're symbolic creatures,
we can build symbolic descriptions
of relations and events.
We can string them together and make stories.
And because we can make stories,
that's what makes us different.
So that's my stump speech.
That's how I start most of my talks
on my own personal research.
How do you,
how do you express the notion
that you've done something?
By listing the steps that need to be taken
in order to achieve the solution to that problem.
You don't have to have done all of those steps,
but you can say,
here's what needs to be done.
An example.
Here's what needs to be done.
We need to specify some behavior.
We need to enumerate the constraints
that make it possible to deal with that behavior.
We have to implement a system
because we're engineers
and we don't think that we've understood something
unless we can build it.
And we've built such a system
and we're about to demonstrate it to you today.
That would be an example of enumerating
a series of steps needed to realize the vision.
So then, blah, blah, blah,
blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
And then you conclude by,
you conclude by enumerating your contributions.
It's kind of a mirror of these steps
and helps to establish that you've done something.
So that's a kind of general purpose framework
for doing a technical talk.
Now, only a few more things left to do today.
Getting famous is the next item on our agenda
because once you've got the job,
you need to think a little bit about
how you're going to be recognized for what you do.
So.
Well, first of all,
why should you care about getting famous?
I thought about this in connection with a fundraising event
I attended once.
Fundraising event for raising money to save Venice
from going underwater and having all of its art destroyed.
Anyway, I was sitting here.
And JC was sitting here.
That was Julia, the late Julia Child.
And as the evening wore on,
more and more people would come up
and ask Julia to autograph something
or express a feeling that she had changed their life.
And it just happened over and over again.
So eventually, I turned to Julia and I said,
Ms. Child, is it fun to be famous?
And she thought about it
for a second and she said,
you get used to it.
But you know what occurred to me?
You never get used to being ignored.
So it's, you know, it's, it's. . .
Here's a way to think about it.
Your ideas are like your children.
And you don't want them to
go into the world in rags.
So what you want to do is
to be sure that you have these techniques,
these mechanisms, these thoughts about how
to present the ideas that you have
so that they're recognized for
the value that is in them.
So that's why it's a legitimate thing
to concern yourself with packaging.
Now, how do you get remembered?
Well, there's something I like to call Winston's Star.
And every one of the items
I'm about to articulate has a,
starts with an S.
So if you want your name to be remembered,
if you want your presentation ideas to be remembered,
one of the things you need to
do is to make sure that you have
some kind of symbol associated with your work.
So this arch example is actually from
my PhD thesis many, many years ago.
And in the course of my work at that time,
this work on arch learning became
mildly famous and I didn't know why.
It was only many years later that I realized that
that work was really important to me.
And I realized that this work accidentally
had all of the elements on this star.
So the first element is that
there was a kind of symbol.
It's the arch itself.
Next thing you need is some kind of slogan.
A kind of phrase that
provides a handle on the work.
And in this case, the phrase was,
one shot learning.
And it was one shot
because the program I wrote learned something definite
from every example that was presented to us.
So in going from a model based on this configuration
to something that isn't an arch based on that configuration,
the program learned that it has to be on top.
One shot learning.
So that's a symbol, slogan.
Now we need a surprise.
The surprise is you don't need
a million examples of something to learn.
You can do it with one example
if you're smart enough to
make use of that example appropriately.
So that was the surprise.
You can learn something definite from each example.
Next item was the salient idea.
Now when I say salient idea, I don't mean important.
What I mean is an idea that sticks out.
Some theses, funnily enough, have too many good ideas
and you don't know what it's
all about because which one is it?
So you need an idea that sticks out.
And the idea that stuck out here
was the notion of a near miss.
You see, this is not an
arch, but it doesn't miss by much.
So it's a near miss.
And finally, you need to tell the story.
Of how you did it,
how it works, why it's important.
So that's a bit on how
to not so much get famous,
but how to ensure that your work is recognized.
We're almost finished because now
we're down to this last item,
which is how to stop.
And when we come to that, there's a question of,
all right, well, what is the final slide?
And what are the final words?
So for the final slide, let
me give you some examples of possibilities.
How about this one?
Well, you might see that slide and think to yourself,
there are a thousand faculty at MIT.
Nice piece of work, but not so much,
but it's only a tiny piece of
work if you divide by a thousand.
So you show a whole gigantic list
of collaborators at the end of a talk.
It's a kind of letdown
because it suggests that nobody knows,
well, did you do anything significant?
Now, you've got to recognize your collaborators, right?
So where do you do that?
Not on the last slide.
On the first slide.
All this was on the first slide.
These are the collaborators.
So you don't want to put them at the end.
You don't want a slide like this.
How about this one?
This is the worst possible way to end a talk
because this slide can be up there for 20 minutes.
I've seen it happen.
It squanders real estate.
It squanders an opportunity to tell people who you are.
It's just...
What about this one?
I often see it.
I've never seen anybody write it down.
Also, it wastes opportunity.
Oh, my God.
Even worse.
All of these slides do nothing for you.
They waste your time.
They waste an opportunity for you to tell people,
to leave people with what you...
with who you are.
Well, what about this?
This a good one?
It might seem so at first,
but here's the problem.
If you say these are my conclusions,
these are perfectly legitimate conclusions
that nobody cares about.
What they care about is what you have done.
And that's why your final slide should have this label.
Contributions.
It's a mirror of what I said over there
about how job talks ought to be like a sandwich.
And the final slide, the one that's up there
while people are asking questions and filing out,
it ought to be the one
that has your contributions on it.
Here's an example from my own stump speech.
Yeah, this is what I talk about a lot.
Yes, here are the things that I typically demonstrate.
And I wait for people to read it.
And then the final element there is
this is what we get out of it.
So that's an example of a contribution slide.
All right, now, what about the other part?
You know, you've got your final slide up there.
It's a contribution slide.
Somehow you have to tell people you're finished.
So let's check out a few possibilities.
One thing you could do in the final words
is you could tell a joke.
It's okay.
By the time you're done, people have adjusted themselves
to your voice parameters.
They're ready for a joke.
I was sitting in another
bar this time in Austin, Texas,
with a colleague of mine named Doug Lenat.
And he said,
Doug's a fantastic speaker.
And so I said to Doug,
Doug, you're a fantastic speaker.
What's your secret?
And he said,
Oh, I always finish with a joke,
and that way people think
they've had fun the whole time.
So, yeah, a joke will work down there.
How about this one?
Thank you.
I don't recommend it.
It's a weak move.
You will not go to
hell if you conclude your talk
by saying thank you, but it's a weak move.
And here's why.
When you say thank you, even worse,
thank you for listening,
it suggests that everybody has stayed that long
out of politeness,
and that they had a
profound desire to be somewhere else,
but they're so polite they stuck it out.
And that's what you're thanking them for.
So once wild applause has started,
you can mouth a thank you,
and there's nothing wrong with that.
But the last thing you do
should not be saying thank you.
Now you say to me,
Well, doesn't everybody say thank you?
Well, what everybody does is
not necessarily the right thing.
And I'd like to illustrate how some talks can end
without saying thank you.
I like to draw from political speeches,
but the ones that I've heard recently aren't so good.
So I'm going to have
to go back a little bit.
So here's Governor Christie.
He gave the Republican keynote address one year.
This is the end of his talk.
Let's see what he does.
And together, everybody, together,
we will stand up once again,
for American greatness for our children and grandchildren.
God bless you, and God bless America.
That's a classic benediction ending.
God bless you, God bless America.
Now, I don't want to be partisan about this,
so I think I'd better switch to the keynote address
and the Democratic Convention.
I was delivered that year by Bill Clinton,
who knows something about how to do politics.
Who knows something about how to speak.
If that is what you want,
if that is what you believe,
you must vote and you must re-elect
President Barack Obama.
God bless you, and God bless America.
Now, watch this.
Let's go back a little bit and redo it.
What I want you to
see is that at one point,
he seems to be almost pressing his lips together,
forcing himself not to say thank you.
Then there's another place where he does a little salute.
So watch for those this time around.
If that is what you want,
if that is what you believe,
you must vote and you must re-elect
President Barack Obama.
God bless you, and God bless America.
That's where his person is.
That's where he's pressing his lips.
There's a salute.
Yeah, I think that's pretty good.
Now, what are we going to take away from this?
Well, I suppose I could conclude this talk by saying,
God bless you, and God bless America.
Institute of Technology.
But it might not work so well.
But what you can get out of this
is you don't have to say thank you.
There are other things you can do.
And you know, it's interesting that over time,
people figure this out,
and there are some stock ways of ending things.
So in the Catholic Church,
in the good old Latin Mass,
it landed with,
Iti miss est,
which translates approximately to,
Okay, the Mass is over.
You can go home now.
And of course, at musical concerts,
you know that it's time to close.
You know that it's time to close.
It's time to clap.
Not at the end of the song,
but rather when the conductor goes over
and shakes hands with the concertmaster.
Those are conventions that tell
you that the event is over.
So those are all possibilities for here.
But one more possibility,
and that is that you can salute the audience.
And by that, I mean you can say something about
how much you value your time at a place.
So I could say,
Well, it's been great fun being here.
It's been fascinating to see what
you folks are doing here at MIT.
I've been much stimulated and provoked
by the kinds of questions you've been asked.
It's been really great.
And I look forward to coming
back on many occasions in the future.
So let's salute to the audience.
You can do that.
Well, there it is.
You know what?
I'm glad you're here.
And the reason is by being here,
I think you have demonstrated an understanding
that how you present and how you package your ideas
is an important thing.
And I salute you for that.
And I suggest that you come
back again and bring your friends.
Thank you.
You may be CHANGE Nothing.